my talk is about flashing ECU firmware
updates from a web browser more
specifically I did some reverse
engineering of the Honda firmware update
file format that they put out so that's
when were you talking about so Who am I
my name is greg hogan you can follow me
on twitter all the source code for the
software that i'm going to show you is
open-source you can find it in one or
more my github repositories and I work
at common AI on infrastructure which yes
you're wondering that has nothing to do
with car hacking
so a couple days ago I got an email and
it's a DEFCON 27 talk and I thought oh
this is information on like my speaking
gig here I opened up the email and no it
is from Honda so apparently they were
interested in my talk and I'll summarize
this for you it basically says don't do
something that might kill somebody that
was never my intention I won't be for
some reason they thought that I was
probably going to be releasing specific
modifications about making firmware
modifications to power steering
controllers of Honda vehicles that's not
the case I never planned on talking
about anything like that so that doesn't
change anything that I'm going to be
talking about also this is a completely
legitimate thing to ask of someone to
make sure you don't do something that
could injure somebody and I agree
completely that trying to make changes
to your electronic power steering
firmware of your car could be very
dangerous if you screw something up the
best case might be that the steering
wheel tries to break your arms and the
worst case is it'll flip over your car
and kill you so please don't do anything
stupid and I have no intention of
enabling you to be able to do such
things
what got me interested in flashing ECU
firmware updates so in 2017 George Hotz
he's actually the guy that started the
company that I worked for he gave a talk
at code blue at a conference where he
kind of showed some you kind of showed
some information about like how you can
get these firmware updates from
different vehicle manufacturers and I
looked at these tools that he was
showing and I thought wow that's
software's garbage it looks like it runs
on like Windows XP and why isn't anyone
created anything better so that's kind
of what I what I set out to do
and I guess to to do that to enable that
in like a modern web development stack
that's why I decided to see if I could
make this work where I could flesh ECU's
from web browsers
it's basically what I'm going to show
you how to do is basically similar to
what like there so there's a whole
community of people who go out there and
they make changes to do like engine
tuning for their ECU's change like gas
fuel mixtures and stuff like that
they've basically done what I'm going to
show you they've figured out you know
how the firmware updates work for in
what I'm going to show you here Honda
vehicles and then they figure out how to
flash their own firmware updates
essentially without using the Honda
software to do so that they distribute
so how do you get the software and
firmware updates for these vehicles so
thanks to write to repair vehicle
manufacturers are basically required to
provide at a reasonable cost the
firmware updates for the tools basically
that enable any maintenance shop to be
able to do repair work so that you're
not like locked into going to a holiday
dealership and them like charging you
and I'm gonna like to do this kind of
stuff so anyone can sign up for these
these these websites Honda is really
cheap ten dollars for one day to
download the software that they provide
to their you know to their repair shops
and anyone who's like you know a repair
shop that repairs Honda vehicles they'll
you know subscribe to this also if you
subscribe for one day interestingly you
actually get three days so Toyota's a
little more expensive and you know
there's other vehicle manufactures well
I guess just one that does like over the
year updates and you don't have you you
know if you have the right access to
your car the firmware updates are
actually pushed to your vehicle so you
don't have to like pay to get them
so so I signed up and I downloaded the
software and I wish I could get that
four hours of my life back that it took
to install it it's horrible just like
from a UI perspective usability
perspective it's not great software the
authentication is over HTTP
like nobody's proud of themselves for
like working on the software I don't
think this is the new version this is
new for like I think like 2017 model
year vehicles or something like that the
old version looked even sadder
it's called HDS Honda for Honda its
Honda Diagnostics system in 2017 when
this new version came out they threw an
eye in the front of it my guess is
they're like trying to ride the Apple
train you know bandwagon or something
like I Oh s and so forth but using this
software is nothing like using an Apple
product you also need a piece of
hardware to interface with the car
through the ODB to port so that hardware
there's if you go to the Honda website
there's one there's one like certified
Hardware package that you can buy and it
is almost $1,500
sad because like it just does like stuff
that follows specifications that are
open you know that anyone can implement
because of right to repair basically
so one of those boxes on like that first
window was something called the J the J
2 v 3 for rewrite tool so what is that
thing that's the software that actually
does the firmware updates that actually
flashes your ECU's so the company I work
for they actually make an obd2 dongle
that has a USB port called a panda and
it's a lot cheaper than $1,500 product
that Honda sells it has an open-source
j2 534 driver which is basically the API
that that like the whatever for like
emissions testing and so forth they
defined it so that you know to enable
write to repair essentially and the
driver like it's not perfect but it'll
East works for can and so so I decided
to go down this path since it's so much
more cost-effective and the Panda has it
has a great Python library for
interacting with your vehicle over the
obd2 port and someone wrote a web USB
driver for it so I'll get into that a
little bit more but that's a big part of
what enables me being able to flash an
ECU from a web browser
so that four hours that I spend
installing the software on a really fast
machine another thing that it drops
alongside this executable is the actual
firmware updates so that's how you get
the actual firmware update files and
they're in this folder here that I
listed button
so okay now we've got a flashing tool
and we've got firmware updates so now
what we want to do is we want to reverse
engineer you know whatever the process
is so that I can replicate it and build
my own software that actually does this
so the first thing that I found was this
software called J 2 v 3 for lager
basically what that does is it acts as a
proxy to a real j2 5:34 driver the the J
2 v 3 4 spec so the reason part of the
reason that this software I did guess I
didn't mention this this Honda software
it only runs on Windows and the reason
that it only runs on Windows is because
the j2 5:34 API specifies things like
use these registry keys to find a dll
and load it so that's another reason
that I was interested in creating my own
software that flashes this because you
know if you break out of that you can
you know make something that's like
cross-platform there runs on a web
browser which should be cool
so basically you can you can fire up
that j2 five three four rewrite tool the
Honda puts out and fire up this install
this logger and if you have a vehicle
that has an ECU that has an update you
can apply it yourself with this software
and you can record it and it'll dump out
this big log file that has all the j2
534 API calls as well as like the raw
data that was sent and received back and
forth so then to you know kind of dig
deeper into what the actual steps are
that happened when you flash a honda ECU
firmware update we need to start
understanding some of these other specs
UDS unified Dinan gnostics that's like a
big one it has all the like commands
that j2 534 uses to actually communicate
with ECU make it feel like security
access key exchange and all these things
and send the firmware the next layer
down is is OTP I mention we just
mentioning these things because this is
what I have to implement if I'm going to
implement my own and a web browser
because as far as I know no one has
written one in JavaScript
all right so after recording flashing an
ECU from that j25 3/4 rewrite tool that
honda distributes here's what you come
up with basically more or less an
eight-step process here the first thing
that you have to do is you have to these
are all the names on the right are the
UDS message types essentially that you
have to send to communicate with your
car so basically you need to enter you
need to send a session control message
because you can't you can't request a
security access seed until you've gotten
into that specific diagnostic session
mode once you get there you can request
a seed you'll then see you'll then see
the seed go back to the software
software then does a manipulation to
that seed sends back a key and that key
is what allows you to do the next step
which is enter a programming session so
this is what we want to get to right we
want to be able to we want to get the
ECU to the state where we can actually
send and change the firmware on it
then things get dangerous like from a oh
crap I might brick my ECU perspective
because the next thing that you do is
you erase the memory that you want to
write after you erase it you you have to
send this message that is it turns out
what it is is you're sending it some
some keys that go to the firmware so
that it can decrypt the firmware that
you're going to send it so it turns out
that these Honda firmware update files
the firmware portion of the file
they actually encrypted and the ajaita
5:3 for rewrite tool it doesn't decrypt
it it sends it to the ECU and then the
ECU decrypt it so they haven't
distributed per se any software that you
can obtain that actually has like the
the decryption algorithm in it it's all
needs to you
then you you know proceeded to send the
firmware and then at the very end it
does basically checksum you send a
message that performs this validation
which I believe what it does is
validates that the check sums in the
firmware correct the check sums in the
Honda firmware extremely poor they're
actually just the sum of all the bytes
across a few sections so so I don't know
like that's kind of crappy a bit you
know a couple bit flips and and yeah you
might have might have you might not have
what you thought you had there
all right so this firmware update file I
mentioned earlier on that there's a
folder that gets dropped that has all
these firmware update files in it and
those firmware update files have a
certain format that I'm now going to go
through and explain you know what the
different pieces are because my ultimate
goal here is to create a website that I
choose one of these firmware update
files and I then flash it to an ECU as
if I you know was that j2 five three
four rewrite tool but without any Honda
any software written by Honda so the
very first bite of the file is what I
call the signature it basically tells
you the format of the rest of the file
there's a few different formats I'm just
gonna focus on one because I only care
about one which is can there's also
other formats I think where like you
flash over Lin or other other protocols
but I'm just gonna focus on can because
that's probably like the future at least
for any vehicle that I'm going to own
SOCAN is this in this hex 5a about you
all right so now the next section after
that first bite now we're in the cans
specific format of the firmware update
and there's six header fields these six
header fields they basically have
everything that you need to be able to
look at one of these firmware update
files determine if the car that you're
plugged into has an ECU that a specific
firmware update file applies to and if
it's running a version of firmware that
is supported as an update or if the file
is an update for the version of the
firmware that's on the ECU so you only
need a few things you need the can
address of the ECU that you want to know
if you can update with the specific
firmware filed so there's one byte that
specifies it the reason it's a single
byte is because like if you look at the
spec 29 bit addresses there's only one
significant byte so they just have that
one byte in there and then there's a few
different values like they can change
these security access keys per firmware
update file so they put the actual keys
in the firmware update file
because you have to send them to the ECU
so when the ECU receives the firmware it
knows how to decrypt it and then there's
also a key that I'll get into in a
minute here that is an input to the
security access key exchange so what you
need to do to get that ECU into
programming mode essentially
after the headers is the actual firmware
this is the encrypted firmware that I
talked about before there's a start
address in a length when you that
sequence that I laid out a couple of the
steps were saying okay what section of
firm word do I want to flash on the ECU
and how much data am I now going to send
that's part of that UDS sequence of
messages that you have to send to the
ECU it the the honda ECU's i've looked
at they actually only allow you to flash
one section of the firmware they did a
pretty good job in terms of like making
it kind of hard to brick the device
because the bootloader is outside of the
area that they allow you to flash so
that's good but yeah the state is
encrypted so we can't really look at the
firmware at this point
and then at the end of the file is a
checksum and it's just the sum of all
the bytes except the checksum itself and
so that is that's the entirety of one of
these can format honda firmware update
files all right the encryption so I
mentioned that this firmware is like the
data section of the update file for the
firmware is encrypted so I thought ok
well in the interesting to see if we can
decrypt that and the talk that I
mentioned at the beginning that got me
kind of interested in this George's code
blue talked he shows one algorithm that
they used for encryption and I thought
to myself oh ok well maybe I'm lucky
maybe they use the same encryption for
every one of these updates it turns out
that's not the case but there was these
keys that we already found in the
headers of each firmware update file so
I've got the keys I've got an example so
what should I try ok well maybe they
just change the operators
it turns out at least somewhat common
that's the case and it's not too hard to
write a piece of software in Python that
just brute force tries every combination
of operators that result in a full 256
value lookup table where every value is
you know the input is unique to the
output so utilizing that I wrote this
piece of software that I linked to it
that's out there called RWD x-ray and
that it does that exactly it it'll you
give it a firmware update file and it
will try to find it'll try to find a set
of operators based on the keys in the
RWD file to be able to decrypt the
firmware
yeah so that's really fast most these
firmware updates are small and yeah it
takes like seconds to to run this
through and find the find the
appropriate operators for a lot of them
doesn't seem to work on all of them
which makes me think that maybe they
actually use like a different algorithm
for some firmware updates but it seems
like there's a number of them that they
actually use the same basic algorithm
with just different operators
so this is just an example of running
that tool it just kind of it ties
everything together that I just talked
through it basically you know parses the
file spits out the headers the way that
it figures out if it has successfully
decrypted the firmware is that there's a
UDS message that you can send to request
the software version of an ECU to get
the firmware version of an ECU that
returns something that looks like a part
number for Honda with an extra little
bit of an extra few numbers at the end
all of these RWD files have a name
that looks like a part number so what I
do is I take the beginning portion of
the RWD file and I say every time I try
a set of operators do I find in the
decrypted firmware a string that matches
that and normally there's just one down
the bottom there all those dots is it
trying every possible set of operators
that existed and the X means it hit and
it actually found the string that it was
looking for in this brute force way of
going through the different
possibilities of all the algorithms
[Music]
and then it spits out the decrypted
firmware into a file at the end
okay so my goal here is to flash an ECU
from a web browser and I now completely
understand this firmware update file
that honda has that honda publishes that
anyone can get ahold of it has
everything in it I guess except the
actual security access key exchange
algorithm so I know I figured out
everything I need to figure out to flash
an ECU myself you know write my own
software that does it but I don't know
how to make it through the security
access key exchange their security
access key changes okay it it generates
a random two byte number and then you
have to manipulate it and send back the
corresponding response that is the
correct response going you know after
you manipulate it with security access
key exchange algorithm but we don't know
what that is so a brute force would take
a long time it's probably actually maybe
doable but if you do it you've now
figured it out for one ECU for
potentially one single firmware revision
of that ECU so what else would have this
security access key exchange that I
already have access to
well how about that j25 3/4 reflash tool
turns out it's pretty easy to find the
security access key extraño algorithm in
that tool and it looks like as far as I
can tell they basically use the same
algorithm to a similarly simple
algorithm just you know addition
multiplication and modulo so basically
the same algorithm there's just like one
variation whether the whether the key
that's in the file is 2 or what 4 bytes
or 6 bytes and so yeah great now we
found how to get through the security
access key exchange for probably any
honda ECU at least that his flash Dover
can most likely and I guess like all the
people that do like the engine tuning
ECU tuning I guess they all know this I
don't know I guess it was easy to find
though so I guess it makes sense that
they would
all right so I've got everything I want
or I need to know now to build this
website so I created this website it's
open source auto ECU dot IO is the URL
it's the auto ECU github repository that
I have it's open source it's it only
supports this Panda ODB 2 dongle that
that I'm using here because I don't know
any other any other ODB - dongle that
supports the web USB driver that Chrome
has so that you can interact with a USB
device directly from from a web browser
this website is just static content like
you don't need an internet connection to
use it there's no API you can don't you
can totally just pull down the github
repo and run it locally but you know for
convenience I just threw it up on auto
ECU IO
[Music]
there are some problems it's not perfect
now this isn't like productionize code
so don't use it on something that you're
not willing to replace if you end up
breaking your ECU I actually opened a
chrome a chrome issue because in their
effort to curb people doing crypto
mining in your web browsers like through
ads and so forth they don't let tabs
that are like in the background or don't
have focus keep executing code
indefinitely or maybe they only give it
like small time slices or something so
like for example when you use this you
really want to keep the browser focused
because because like you switch tabs and
then basically the flashing process
applause this so you really don't want
that to happen you know what in the
middle generally it's like it's okay
like if you cancel flashing one of these
ECU's in them in the middle you've
potentially erased the ECU but since the
bootloader is at the beginning if you
haven't done anything really dumb and if
you're not really unlucky you can just
you can just cycle the power and start
over and flash again but yeah it's
definitely possible that you'll brick an
ECU if you use this so I have a little
video here I have a 20-17 honda cr-v it
has ECU updates for several ACU's let's
play this here
see if I can make it fullscreen here if
you watch the - really close things look
pretty good right now it looks normal
I'm like picking the firmware file right
now does a little validation and then
I'm gonna start the flashing process
here and then holy every error code
possible pops up on the dash so I don't
know if I like miss maybe I missed
something maybe there's like some way to
prevent that from happening but it's
kind of scary I mean I tested this like
on a bench before and actually like had
bugs in my code like for example when
you plug when you plug into one ECU
sitting on a bench there's no other
ECU's on the canvas so like you can make
a mistake where your software assumes
accidentally that there's only what that
every message that's coming is intended
for you know your software when you know
the ECU's are throwing messages all over
the place all the time and so luckily
that was easy to fix and now now it
works better in like actually this
successfully flashes the ECU looks like
it's flashing right now actually
applying the firmware I think this is
like applying the radar firmware update
for my car or something like that so
I've just I just took you know the the
RWD file the Honda names these firmware
update files but RWD is the extension
I just took that you know selected in
the software that I'll show you a live
demo here in a minute of an ECU on a
bench and picked it and flashed it and
then I just power cycled the car and all
the ears went away so that's great work
Thanks
so so that was fun but you know these
these ECU engine tuner guys they don't
just flash the updates that they you
know get from Honda they reverse
engineered this and they generate their
own updates right so wouldn't it be more
fun if we you know we could you know
figure out how to generate an update
maybe for an ECU that doesn't even have
an update and then flash that so you
don't need a whole lot of information
you just need you know whatever is in
that RWD file you can just make up some
keys you do have to be able to figure
out you know how to get firmware off of
an ECU
maybe or you could like I guess start
with one of those our double D files if
you wanted to just to play around with
generating your own and but you got to
be able to get you know the firmware you
have to be able to encrypt it since it's
encrypted in these are two BD update
files but this is actually like a pretty
good format for updating an ECU because
it's like self-contained it's a
self-contained file and it has
everything in it you need to be able to
flash an ECU and validate that you know
the ECU that you're going to flash is
running you know an expected version of
firmware before you flash it and and so
forth so so
in my RWE x-ray repo there is a script
that does just that if you supply it an
encrypted firmware file like what you
would find in one of the RWD files in
the firmware section and the appropriate
headers then it'll kick out for you an
are WD file that you can flash using my
website alright so let's do that I have
I just just because out of convenience I
have an ECU here that I tore apart to
play around with and it's you can get
for example a lot of ECU's on you know
like LQK online for really cheap this is
specifically an ECU for the electronic
power steering for my 2017 Honda CRV I'm
just using it because like that's what I
have out of convenience so let's let's
do it
so yeah so basically I just I was it I
figured out how to extract the firmware
from the CCU I used that are to be
builder to what I did was just build you
know for proof of concept
I built a firmware update that does
nothing it literally just is the
original firmware on the ECU so that's
we're gonna do so this is this is my web
sorry this is my website auto ECU IO and
right now it has to drop down for
manufacturer Honda is the only
manufacturer that is supported but you
know it's open-source if someone's
interested they could you know
definitely add formats of other firmware
update files distributed by other car
manufacturers I'd looked a little bit I
like Tesla's firmware update file format
and it's like so much simpler than the
Honda for example it just has like I
think it has like a header that says the
start address in the length and then
it's just the firmware just you know not
encrypted or anything so you could
definitely expand this you know if you
wanted to the other thing too is like
you know I can mention it being that
that honda diagnostic software is is so
hard to use and and slow and a pain to
install you can do all kinds of cool
stuff with this too right like one of
the great things about the honda
software is like you can get deep
introspection into if you get like check
engine lights and so forth what those
things you know what are those check
engine lights and being able to clear
them and so forth so like you can easily
you know take this in and for example
build your own hds that enabled you to
you know more easily maybe clear check
engine codes from a web browser so
there's all kinds of cool stuff you can
do with this
so let me power this it's powered on
here I don't know if anyone can really
see this here sorry we didn't get a
table
so this chair here is my what's that oh
hey I got a table I'm gonna go grab the
table quick thanks
all right so this may be the step
deserves a little more explanation here
so this doesn't really look like
electronic power steering this because
it's like all tore apart and like the
controller in this situation is not
separate from the motor they actually
put the controller in the motor so
that's why it's like all tore apart and
weird I'm using one of those panda obd2
dongles that comment I sells and the red
thing plugged in is just so that I have
a long USB a long enough USB cord that's
called a panda paw it's just in case
like you brick your your obd2 dongle you
can actually you actually can't really
brick it because you can use this panda
pod to get it in Adi a few boot mode so
that's plugged into another thing that
we sell which you don't need by any
means at all it's just it's just like a
development board that breaks out the
the obd2 pins really conveniently so I
just use that to build an adapter to go
from the ECU from like the real ECU
connector to the Panda PO db2 connector
so advice
so yeah so all right let's pull up this
is my fake firmware update that is just
like the stock firmware that I generated
a file for because there is no firmware
update for this ECU I picked that from R
update file and I say next now this is
where those headers that are in the RWD
file come into play it just it just went
out and so I implemented that UDS
protocol and the is OTP I am I
implemented in JavaScript you can see it
in one of my in the github repo for this
for this website so like it just went
off and it just worried that can address
180 a 3-0 F 1 and I think it might have
sound like tester present
or something like that I know I'm sorry
they didn't send it off yet we start to
connect to the ECU
so the way web USB works for like
security reasons is if you have a device
implements the web USB protocol when you
plug into your computer it doesn't just
like get access to things so Chrome has
this specification where there's there's
a JavaScript call you can make to say go
you know go talk to this USB device and
then it prompts the user to actually say
yes you're allowed to talk to this USB
device from a web browser
so I pick it I say connect okay now now
it actually went out and it actually
like sound like tester present to the
ECU and said like are you there are you
awake
and then there's another UDS message
called
like read memory by address I think it's
read memory by address and there's a
specific code that's defined that
there's like four of them they're like
loader versions software version
application version so I think it's I
think it's software version it goes off
and it queries the software version and
it checks does the software version that
the ECU returned match what my RWD
headers excuse me what my RWD headers
say are the supported software versions
for this for a more update file alright
so now we're connected next okay this is
the danger screen like I said you can
brick an ECU so don't do this with an
ECU that you're not willing to pay to
replace something could go wrong I say I
agree and flash it's erasing the memory
and now it's flashing the firmware so
it's basically just going to that
sequence they laid out at the very
beginning to actually send the firmware
update so you can can't really see the
progress bar there really well but it's
like 25 percent and moving along
LEDs are like flashing different colors
on the table over here
yeah so I know once you have this I
guess flashing a firmware updates pretty
boring
it'll be done here in a second a few
seconds about 80% and then I'll just
pull something up like this ECU just
constantly dumps out some messages on
the canvas okay it's complete so all
right let's talk to this ECU I got to
free up the USB device the web browser
doesn't have a hold of it and all right
so let's see if this all right so it
should be now if I didn't hopefully this
is where like the live demo doesn't go
all wrong if I try to connect to this
ECU and read all the messages that it's
dumping out on the canvas
there you go so it's like five messages
that just dumps out I think it's like a
torque sensor that's on it and a bunch
of other stuff so
so yeah and I guess that's it that's my
talk what's up
[Applause]
I
yeah sure so is there any signature on
the firmware no yeah there's no
signature it just like they just there's
there's that last step where they say
they say basically validate the firmware
there's like a routine control message
that gets called and that validation is
just our that check do the checks that
do the do the do this some of the bytes
add up so yeah so yeah there's nothing
like that did it and then the other
comment was I made some assumptions
about like I had something I wanted to
decrypt it and I didn't know you know
what the how I would do I know like how
would I make those assumptions so that I
know when it was decrypted completely or
properly yeah so I mean I just guessed
right and then in addition to guessing
though this ECU here is tore apart
because then I have the decrypted
firmware like I figured out how to dump
the full firmware so so like these
firmware update files they're you know
potentially not super useful to modify
because they're partial right like
important things that you want to modify
or you need to like reverse engineering
out of them they might not even be in
the update section right so like what I
did was I got an ECU that I was able to
dump the firmware off of and then I just
had these ideas like okay well I should
be able to find this software version
that you can request through read memory
by address and maybe it's like I just
tried like okay well maybe how many
times I had no idea how many times how
many sets of
you know combinations of operators and
my brute-force decryption would match
and it turned out like 99% of the time
there was only one and I had the real
firmware from an ECU to compare to to
then make a hundred percent certain that
at least sometimes I was decrypting it
successfully
this one actually this specific ECU is
simpler than that it's it's UART its
serial but a lot of them are JTAG that
you you have to dump them too
yep yeah
no I don't think so I mean they don't
they don't they don't publish any
firmware updates I think George is like
set on our discord multiple times at all
for more modifications or cancelled so
yeah I mean this is just you know this
is just me working on this stuff in my
free time basically so yeah this is just
my stuff for fun so yeah
yeah so I haven't had that much time to
like really work on it and make it
awesome so like I just tried it on a few
ECU's that are actually in my car but I
haven't like I haven't specifically
tested it out on like what like the
engine tuning PC you guys do you know
the where there's a lot more potential I
mean they all charge money for that
stuff right well metals and I think
there's some free ones like ROM Raider
or something like that but like I I
think this is the future I think you
know it seems like what browsers are
gonna be the you know the platform for
building modern applications in the
future and and so like I don't I feel
like I'm showing you the future of what
these tools are going to look like
someday
all right
cool thanks guys and I think someone
gave me this adapter thanks a lot for um
the adapter so I could actually give my
presentation
[Applause]